hey what's up guys my name is a Cho and
welcome to another episode of my C++
series So today we're going to learn all
about how C++ Works we're going to kind
of try and keep it simple for now but
we're going to learn about how we go
from the source file the actual text
file to an actual executable binary so
program that we can run the basic
workflow of writing a C++ program is you
have a series of source files which you
write actual text in and then you pass
it through a compiler which compiles it
into some kind of binary now that binary
can be some sort of library or it can be
an actual executable program today we're
going to talk specifically about
executable programs or executable
binaries so let's hop on over to visual
studio and check it out okay so here we
have our hello world application that we
wrote in the previous video when we
learned how to set up C++ on Windows
it's a pretty basic program but there
are quite a number of things going on
here first of all we have this include
IO stream statement now this is
something called a pre-processor
statement anything that begins with a
hash is a pre-processor statement the
first thing that a compiler does when it
receives a source file is it
pre-processes all of your pre-processor
statements that's why they're called
pre-processor statements because they
happen just before the actual
compilation in this case is something
called include what include will do is
find a file so in this case we're
looking for a file called iostream take
all of the contents of that file and
just paste it into this current file
these files that you include are
typically called header files and we'll
discuss them more in depth as the series
goes on the reason we're including
something something called IO stream is
because we need a declaration for a
function called C out which lets us
print stuff to our console next we have
this main function now the main function
is very important because every C++
program has something like this the main
function is called the entry point it's
the entry point for our application that
means that when we run our application
our computer starts executing code that
begins in this function as the program
is running our computer will execute the
lines of code that we type in order of
course there are certain things that can
break or change the order of execution
and those are primarily called control
flow statements or calls to other
functions but the gist is that our code
gets executed line by line so the first
thing that will get executed in our
application will be this hello world C
out statement and then the next thing is
this cin.get function and then since
that's all that we've got inside our
main function our program will terminate
now for those of you who are familiar
with functions you might notice that the
return type for main is actually int
however we're not returning an integer
that's because the main function is
actually a case you don't have to return
any kind of value from the main function
if you don't return anything it will
assume that you're returning zero this
only applies to the main function though
it's a special case all right so let's
talk a little bit more about what this
is actually doing this kind of syntax
might look strange for someone who's new
to C++ and it is a little bit
unfortunate that it's actually written
this way because it doesn't make too
much sense when you first look at it but
basically these left angular brackets
which look kind of like a bit shift left
operator are actually just an overloaded
operator so you need to think of them as
a function now I know they look like an
operator but here's the thing operators
are just functions so in this case this
would actually be the same thing as if
it was something like c. print and then
hello world is our parameter and then
maybe we would follow it on along with
another
print that's all it is you have to think
of these operators as functions and if
you think of them that way then this
makes a little bit more sense so what
we're actually doing here is we're
pushing this hollow World string into
this C out which basically causes it to
get printed to the console and then
we're pushing an end line this end line
basically just tells our console to
advance to the next line the cn. getet
function in our case will basically just
wait until we press enter before
advancing to our next line of code which
is nothing so basically what I'm saying
is our program's execution will pause on
this line until we press enter Because
this function is just going to wait for
us to press enter and then we advance to
the next line which is nothing which
means that we actually return zero
meaning our program executed successful
sucessfully and that's it that is our
entire program okay so that's our source
file we've actually got a file called
main.cpp which is a source file how do
we get from this text to an actual
executable binary file so basically we
go through a few stages first we have
this include IO stream this is something
called a pre-processor statement so this
pre-processor statement gets evaluated
before we compiled the file in this case
what it does is it includes all of the
contents of the io stream file into this
file and I mean literally it just it
copies and pastes that file into this
file and again as I said we will talk
about header files in more depth in the
future so don't worry too much if you
don't understand this for now all you
need to know is we include this file so
that we can use the C out and cin
functions once our pre-processor
statements have been evaluated our file
gets compiled this is the stage where
our compiler transforms all of this C++
code into actual
machine code there are several important
settings that determine how this
actually happens so let's take a brief
look at them in Visual Studio we have
these two important drop- down menus up
here one's called a solution
configuration and one's called a
solution platform by default this will
probably be set to debug and then either
x86 or win32 they're actually the same
if we drop down the debug you'll see
that we've got two options debug and
release these two options are defaults
for any new project in visual studio and
then under solution platform you'll see
we've got x64 and X8 6 is our two
options again these are just defaults a
configuration is simply a set of rules
which applies to the building of a
project whereas the solution platform is
what platform we're targeting with our
current compilation so a good example of
that would be x86 is targeting Windows
32-bit which means that we will generate
a 32-bit application for Windows for
more complicated projects where you
might be targeting different platforms
you might have Android as a platform in
that dropdown and then if you wanted to
build and deploy and debug on Android
you would change your platform to be
Android and the solution configuration
is a set of rules that defines the
compilation for that platform so let's
take a look at some of the rules that we
can change in our project let's right
click on it and hit properties so here
we have visual Studios property Pages
these Define the rules that are used to
build certain configurations and
platforms the first thing that you need
to notice is this configuration and
platform area make sure that your config
configuration and your platform is set
to the one that you actually want to
modify for some reason sometimes it
might be set to release however you're
clearly building debug which means that
none of these changes will apply to your
current configuration and if you missed
that you might be wondering why
nothing's working I've had that happen a
few times it's kind of annoying so we've
got our debug configuration you can see
we've got win32 now win32 is exactly the
same as x86 okay they are the same
they've got different names for some
reason but they are the same here we've
got some general information about our
SDK version our output directory our
intermediate directory and stuff like
that the important thing to note here is
that our configuration type is set to
application if we wanted it to be a
library we could we could change it here
but this is basically the binary that
the compiler will output since we're
going for an executable binary we leave
it set to application. EXE the compiler
settings are located under cc++ we've
got important settings here such as
include directories optimization
settings that we may want to use code
generation settings pre-processor
definitions and a whole lot of stuff
that we're not even going to touch
anytime soon the default Visual Studio
configuration is actually pretty good so
we don't really have to do anything but
these are the rules that govern how our
files will get compiled you can see the
difference between the debug and the
release configuration pretty well if you
go into the optimization tab under
optimization if I change this to release
you'll see that the optimization is set
to maximize speed whereas in debug it's
set to disabled that's a great example
of why debug mode by default is slower a
lot slower than release mode because
optimization is turned off but of course
turning off optimization will help us to
debug our code as we will later discover
if you want to know more about how the
compiler works I've made a dedicated
video in depth covering exactly how all
of that happens so go check that out if
you're interested the link will be in
the description below each CPP file in
our project gets compiled header files
do not get compiled at all just CPP
files remember header files get included
via a pre-processor statement called
include into a CP f file and that's when
they get compiled so we've got a bunch
of CPP files that we've compiled and
they actually get compiled individually
every CPP file will get compiled into
something called an object file the
extension for that using visual Studios
compiler is obj once we have all of
those individual obj files which are the
result of compiling our CPP files we
need some way to stitch them together
into one exe file and that's where our
friend the Linker comes in you can see
the Linker settings under this Linker
tab but basically what the the Linker
does is it takes all of those obj files
and it glues them together so the
linker's job is to take all of our obj
files and Stitch them together into one
exe file of course the way that it does
that is actually kind of complicated so
I've made a specific video covering that
go ahead and check that out the link
will be in the description below so
let's take a look at this in action the
first thing I'm going to do is actually
just compile this CPP file in Visual
Studio you can compile files
individually by hitting contrl F7 you
can see our output here shows that we're
actually building this main CVP file and
that it succeeded if you don't want to
hit contr F7 you can actually bring up
this compile button you can do so by
right clicking here and clicking on
build and then going add or remove
buttons customize and then adding a
command under build called compile so if
we hit that button you can see that we
get our file compiling if we were to
make some kind of syntax error here for
example I'm forgetting a semicolon if I
compile that file you'll see that we get
an error now Visual Studio presents us
with errors in many different ways one
of which is this error list and another
way is inside this output window I'm
going to tell you guys right now this
error list is mostly garbage it might
appear to be readable for really small
things like this but you never ever want
to rely on it a lot of the times it's
actually missing information the way
that the error list works is it
basically pauses our output window
looking for the word error and then
grabs information from there that it can
find and puts it into this eror list so
it's it's a good overview you want to
use it like an overview but if you want
more details and if you want all the
information about the error that you've
just had look at the output window so
for the rest of this series I am
actually going to be looking at this
output window for error messages so get
used to that you can see that we've got
an error here it says syntax error
missing semicolon before a curly bracket
it tells you which line number the error
is on if you double click on this actual
line you will be taken to where the
error is in your source code so let's go
ahead and fix that by adding a semicolon
and then hitting contrl F7 or compile to
build this one file so we've compiled a
file when you compile files individually
no linking happens obviously you're just
compiling a single file so the Linker
isn't invoked at all let's go ahead and
check out what the compiler actually
generated if we right click on our
Hollow World project you'll see an open
folder in file explorer button this will
open up our File Explorer by default
visual studio will output our buildt
files into this debug folder and you can
see if we go in there you can see a
main. obj file this is the object file
that our compiler has generated again
you will have one of these for every
single C++ file in your project if we go
back to visual studio and we build the
actual project so I'm doing more than
just building one file here I'm actually
building the entire project you can see
that we actually get that exe file and
again if we go back to our file explorer
that will actually be in the directory
of your solution and then in the debug
folder I know visual Studios default
paths are a little bit weird I usually
like to change them but I'm trying not
to complicate things here and there's
our hello world.exe file which we can
run and imprints the text hello world so
that's a pretty simple overview but what
happens when we have multiple C++ files
let's take a look at a simple example so
suppose that we've got our Hollow World
printing to the console here but I don't
want to use the C out function I want to
use my own logging function and then
maybe that will wrap this out function
so let's create a function called log
which will take in a C string called
message and print that
message to the console simple enough now
don't worry if you're not sure what a
const CH pointer is we're going to talk
about strings in another video for now
all you have to know is that a cons CH
pointer is basically just a type that
can hold a string of text so now we can
rewrite our code so that instead of
calling C out and then printing hello
world we call this log function and then
pass in hello world as a parameter we
can go ahead and hit the local Windows
debugger button here just to make sure
that it still works and you can see it
does fantastic we've written our first
function that was easy so now let's take
that function and put it into a
different file because I don't want to
have this main.cpp file cluttered with
all of my code I want to separate my
code into multiple files to keep things
nice and clean and organized we'll make
a new file under source files by going
right click add new item we'll make a
CPP file we'll call it log.
CPP and we'll click add so what I'm
going to do here is I'm going to go back
to main and I'm going to cut this log
function and paste it into here so now
we've got a function inside our log. CPP
file called log let's try and compile
just this file hey check this out we get
a bunch of errors and if we look at our
output window you'll see that c out is
not a member of STD basically it's
telling us that it has no idea what C
out is the reason is because we haven't
included the Declaration for C out every
kind of symbol in C++ needs some kind of
Declaration C out is defined inside a
file that we included in main.cpp and
that file of course was iostream so
let's go ahead and grab iostream and put
it at the top of this file so that we
include iostream by doing so we include
a declaration for this C out function
let's go ahead and compile this file
once again you can see now it succeeds
great so back in main I want to call
this log function can I do that let's
hit contr F7 no I can't because log is
not found we also get a complaint about
cin but we already know that that's
because we removed the io stream include
and we have no idea what cin is we can
restore that include and our problem
should be fixed however you can see that
log is still not found so what's going
on here we've moved a function from one
file into the other
and we are compiling each file
separately for the minute so this
main.cpp file has no idea that there's a
function called log somewhere and since
it doesn't recognize what log is it
gives us a compile error we can fix this
by providing something called a
declaration a declaration is exactly
what it sounds like we're declaring that
something called log exists now this is
almost like a promise because we can
just say hey compiler there's a function
called log however but the compiler will
just believe us and that's the great
thing about the compiler it'll be like
oh yeah cool I totally trust you because
the compiler doesn't care about
resolving where that log function
actually is defined so we have two
different words here declarations and
definitions declarations are just a
statement which say hey this symbol this
function exists and then a definition is
something that says this is what this
function is this is the body of this
function so let's go ahead and write a
decaration for our log function a
declaration looks very similar to an
actual definition this is something
called a definition because you can see
that not only have we declared something
with the name log a function with the
name log we've also given it a body
which actually contains what code will
run when we call this function so back
in main let's write a declaration and a
declaration looks very similar to a
definition however what it doesn't have
is the actual body so you can see I can
just put a semicolon at the end of this
and that is the end of that in fact you
don't even have to specify the name of
the parameter because it doesn't matter
you can just write that as a rule of
thumb though I do like to specify the
name because it makes more sense so
let's compile this file now Hey look
check this out the compiler totally
bought it so you might be wondering at
this stage well well hey how does the
compiler know that we actually have a
log function in another file if we're
just compiling this one file and the
answer is it doesn't it just it trusts
us so then your second question should
be how does it actually run the right
code that is where the Linker comes in
when we build our entire project not
just this one file but if I actually
right click and hit build once our files
have been compiled the Linker will
actually find the definition of that log
function and wire it up to the log
function that we call here in main.cpp
if it can't find that definition that's
when we get a Linker error now linking
errors are something that look very
scary and a lot of people get scared so
let's go ahead and look at an example of
that so right now if I just run my
program you'll see that it's still
prints out the text hello world and
everything runs successfully however
let's remove this or at least change it
a little bit for example I'll change
this to loger save the file go back here
to main.cpp I'll try and compile this
file by itself you can see that we get
no problems what soever however let's
right click on this Hol world and hit
build and check this out we get a pretty
scary look looking error message which
also unfortunately looks scary in our
output window now the reason this looks
so scary is because it's actually got
some extra information about our
function signature for example it's got
the calling convention here as well as
an actual ID but basically what it's
telling you is that you have an
unresolved external symbol called log
which returns which has this return
value and these parameters and your
referencing this function inside main an
unresolved external symbol means that
the Linker was unable to resolve a
symbol remember linker's job is to
resolve symbols it has to wire up
functions and it couldn't find what to
wire log to because we don't have a
function called log that's actually
defined that has a body so the way that
we can fix this is by fixing our
function we need to provide a definition
for this log function in other words we
have to provide a body for this log
function doesn't have to be inside this
file it can be inside main but it has to
be somewhere and if we compile this
you'll see that we don't get any errors
if we go back to our file explorer and
look at what we've got inside our
intermediate folder here you'll see that
we've got two obj files because the
compiler generates an object file for
each of our CPP files the Linker will
then take them and Stitch them together
into an ex file so in our lovely example
we have our log definition inside this
log obj file and our main function
inside our main. obj file and so the
Linker will basically take that log
definition from log and put it into a
common binary which is our hello
world.exe file which contains a
definition for both Main and log and
that is a basic overview of how C++
works again I highly encourage you to
check out the in-depth videos about how
compiling and linking works because
they're going to be way more information
than this video this video was just made
to show you kind of an overview of the
pipeline of how you go from source files
to an actual binary as always don't
forget to follow me on Twitter and
Instagram
if you really enjoyed this video and you
want to see more you can support me on
patreon I'll see you guys next time
goodbye